TONMOY TALUKDER

https://tonmoytalukder.github.io/ • www.linkedin.com/in/tonmoytalukder/

Dhaka, Bangladesh • (+880) 1880-788228 • tonmoytalukder2000@gmail.com

Areas of Research Interest

I am passionate about researching the utilization of *Multimodal Deep Learning*, *Natural Language Processing*, *Computer Vision* and *Human-Computer Interaction*. I am particularly interested in how to utilize these technologies to improve the understanding and use of low-resource languages.

EDUCATION

• Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Discipline: Computer Science and Engineering

Degree: Bachelor of Science Graduated: May, 2023 **Thesis**: Bengali Key-to-Text: Text Generation from Keywords in Bengali using Pre-trained

Transformers

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

As Research Assistant of Undergrad Supervisor

Dhaka, Bangladesh | (2023 – Present)

• Exploring multimodal research scopes using *LLMs* (*Large Language Models*) in NLG, Computer Vision area for the Bangla language.

Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology

Dhaka, Bangladesh | (2022 – 2023)

- Developed *keyword-extractor* and *sentence generation from keywords technique* for a low-resource language, Bangla. Also developed a dataset for this.
- Explored ranking-based Bengali text summarization.

PUBLICATIONS

Undergrad Thesis:

- Bengali Key-to-Text: Text Generation from Keywords in Bengali using Pre-trained Transformers (Under Review in EMNLP 2023)
 - I have developed a keyword extractor using BERT and a keyword-text pair dataset.
 - I trained T5 that can generate captions from Bengali sentences.

Academic Papers:

• Rank Your Summaries: Enhancing Bengali Text Summarization via Ranking-based Approach (Published) (Corresponding Author)

Authors: G. M. Shahariar*, **Tonmoy Talukder***, Rafin Alam Khan Sotez, and Md. Tanvir Rouf Shawon (* denotes equal contribution, names are listed in alphabetical order).

Conference: International Conference on Big Data, IoT and Machine Learning (BIM 2023)

- Used a BERT text ranker to generate the best summary.
- Applied ensemble approaches. And compared their results.
- Vision2Cap: Bengali Caption Generation from Images using Pre-trained Transformer (Ongoing)
 - I am currently working on the development of a pre-trained LLM transformer-based model aimed at detecting objects and generating image captions in Bangla.
- Additional research insights can be found at: https://tonmoytalukder.github.io/research

July 12, 2023 Page | 1

Presentations

• G. M. Shahariar*, **Tonmoy Talukder***, Rafin Alam Khan Sotez, Md. Tanvir Rouf Shawon. *Rank Your Summaries: Enhancing Bengali Text Summarization via Ranking-based Approach*. Presented at the International Conference on Big Data, IoT and Machine Learning (BIM 2023). (* denotes equal contribution, names are listed in alphabetical order).

Skills

Research: Natural Language Processing, LLM fine Tuning, Computer Vision, Multimodal Learning

Programming Language: Python, JavaScript, C++, SQL (MsSQL), Markup Language (HTML, CSS)

Frameworks: Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, React JS, Node JS, Next JS, Material UI, Tailwind CSS

Tools: Jupyter Notebook (Anaconda 3), Colab, VS Code, Git, LaTeX

Additional Skills: Exploratory Data Analysis, Data Preprocessing, Full Stack Web Development (MERN)

VOLUNTEERING EXPERIENCE

Technovation Bangladesh

Dhaka, Bangladesh

A global tech education nonprofit that empowers girls to become leaders, creators, and problem-solvers.

Mentor December, 2021 – Present

Responsible for...

- Mentoring students to learn App Development, AI & Machine Learning Tools
- Helping students to develop projects for the Technovation Global Competition

ACTIVITIES

- Intra Aust Programming Contest 2019 (7th Position, Junior Division) Ahsanullah University of Science & Technology, Dhaka
- Makers' Mania Programming Contest 2018 (4th Position, Junior Division) Independent University Bangladesh, Dhaka

References

Dr. Md. Shahriar Mahbub, Professor and Head shahriar.cse@aust.edu
Department of Computer Science and Engineering
Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Web: www.aust.edu/cse/faculty member/dr md shahriar mahbub

G. M. Shahariar Shibli, Lecturer

shahariar_shibli.cse@aust.edu

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

Ahsanullah University of Science and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Web: https://shahariar-shibli.github.io/

Sidratul Moontaha, Founder and CEO InnoVerse Foundation, Dhaka, Bangladesh The Diana Award Holder 2021

sidratulmoontaha143@gmail.com

July 12, 2023 Page | 2